{"tossups": [{"question": "The namesake ship of the<em> Mataafa</em> storm was wrecked in this body of water in 1905. Large cobblestone pits built by a pre-Ojibwa people around this body of water are named after a river that flows into it, the Pukaskwa. All 29 crewmembers were killed in a shipwreck on this lake involving a freighter carrying iron ore. Thunder Bay is the largest city that lies along this lake, which also contains Duluth, Minnesota. The <em>SS Edmund Fitzgerald</em> sank in, for ten points, what largest of the Great Lakes?", "answer": "Lake<b> Superior</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s actions sparked Donatist opposition to the \u201ctraditors.\u201d This leader solidified his rule by defeating Carinus at the Battle of the Margus. Causanius led a revolt in Britannia during this ruler\u2019s reign, causing Maximian to be elevated to Augustus. This man was the first Roman emperor to abdicate, retiring to his palace at Split. For ten points, name this emperor who organized the Tetrarchy and conducted the last Christian persecutions.", "answer": "<b> Diocletian</b> (or Gaius Aurelius Valerius<b> Diocletianus</b> Augustus, but do not prompt on partial names thereof; accept<b> Diocles</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This battle\u2019s winners opened fire on William Stevenson\u2019s friendly unit when it insisted on retreating to Helpmekaar. Members of John Chard\u2019s engineers were caught in this battle after they were dispatched to repair pontoon bridges on the Buffalo River. Eleven Victoria Crosses were awarded for this battle, the most ever given to a single regiment. This battle\u2019s winners defended a hospital building on the same day that the Battle of Isandlwana was fought. For ten points, name this 1879 battle in which 100 British troops repelled a Zulu impi.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Rorke\u2019s Drift</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "John Roberts noted that in this ruling, \u201cit\u2019s quite clear that [the Supreme Court isn\u2019t] interpreting the law, they\u2019re making the law.\u201d In one dissent during this case, Oliver Wendell Holmes\u2019s dissent in this case noted \u201cThe Fourteenth Amendment does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer\u2019s<em> Social Statics</em>.\u201d<em> West Coast</em> <em>Hotel Co. v. Parrish</em> ended a forty-year era named for this case in which the Supreme Court consistently sided against economic regulation. For ten points, name this 1905 Supreme Court case that cited due process in overturning a law limiting the work hours of bakers in New York.", "answer": "<b> Lochner</b> v. New York", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In one game in this series, the American government uses the Bay of Pigs invasion as an alibi for a cosmonaut\u2019s injuries sustained during Project Mercury. The end of the Cuban Missile Crisis thwarts the attempted defection of Nikolai Sokolov in this series. The Outer Heaven mercenary company, owned by Ocelot, grows strong enough to challenge world governments in this series\u2019 fourth installment, \u201cThe Guns of the Patriots.\u201d Hideo Kojima created, for ten points, what iconic stealth video game franchise whose protagonist is Solid Snake?", "answer": "<b> Metal Gear</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This right was encouraged by a movement founded by Elizabeth Vesey and Elizabeth Montagu, the Blue Stockings Society. A report by Charles Talleyrand claimed women should only have limited access to this right; a response to that report noted that women only appeared irrational because they were denied this right, which is necessary for women to properly raise their children. Mary Wollstonecraft argued for women\u2019s access to, for ten points, what right, the subject of Jean-Jacques Rousseau\u2019s<em> Emile</em> [ay-meel]?", "answer": "<b> education</b> (accept equivalent answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This kingdom was forced to cede sovereignty to Great Britain by the captain George Paulet. A ruler of this kingdom was aided by Gerrit Judd and proclaimed the Great Mahele [ma-hay-lay] to redistribute land. The unifier of this kingdom protected noncombatants by proclaiming the Law of the Splintered Paddle. A queen of this kingdom was forced to agree to the Bayonet Constitution by American forces. For ten points, name this Pacific kingdom ruled by Kamehameha [ka-MAY-ha-MAY-ha] and Lili\u2019uokalani [LILY-oh-ka-LAH-nee].", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Hawai\u2019i</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The city of Konigsberg was named in honor of a ruler from this region, Ottokar II, who led this region to complete defeat at the hands of Rudolf I at the Battle on the Marchfeld. This region\u2019s Premyslid dynasty was replaced by the House of Luxembourg in 1306. The execution of a preacher at the Council of Constance led to the namesake Hussite Wars in this region. For ten points, name this central European region that makes up most of the Czech Republic.", "answer": "<b> Bohemia</b> (prompt on Czech Republic, but not Czechoslovakia, before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s most famous creation was spawned with the help of Henry Senger and Warren Olney. This man\u2019s theories on valley formation were backed up by the discovery of an alpine glacier below Merced Peak and a later \u201cnoble earthquake\u201d at Lone Pine. This man, who broke with Gifford Pinchot over sheep grazing and the damming of a California valley, was photographed with Teddy Roosevelt atop Glacier Point, part of the Yosemite National Park he helped preserve. For ten points, name this Scottish-American naturalist who founded the Sierra Club.", "answer": "John<b> Muir</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This body\u2019s topography is divided into 30 quadrangles. In 1877, Giovanni Schiaparelli [skap-uh-relli] claimed that canals existed on this body, which was explored by the<em> Viking</em> program. NASA\u2019s<em> Mariner</em> mission discovered the largest known volcano in the solar system,<em> Mons Olympus</em>, on this planet. <em>Opportunity</em> and<em> Spirit</em> explored the surface of, for ten points, what \u201cred\u201d planet, the fourth from the Sun?", "answer": "<b> Mars</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {"question": "This leader once gave a conciliatory speech in English before switching to his native language to say\u201cwe will crush them.\u201d This leader launched a guerrilla war known as the Second Chimurenga, and he outmaneuvered Joshua Nkomo and Bishop Abel Muzorewa to assume control of his country. Ian Smith fought the Rhodesian Bush War against this man\u2019s ZANU-PF party. For ten points, name this autocratic longtime President of Zimbabwe.", "answer": "Robert<b> Mugabe</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Richard Nixon offered to let one of this state\u2019s senators listen to and summarize the White House tapes, probably because he was nearly deaf. In response to the Peekskill riots, John Rankin, a representative from this state, screamed racial slurs on the floor of the House of Representatives. Trent Lott and Thad Cochran resigned as senators from this state, which is currently represented by Roger Wicker and Cindy Hyde-Smith. For ten points, name this southern US state where, in 1964, governor Ross Barnett tried to refuse James Meredith\u2019s enrollment at its state university?", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "At the conclusion of one of this man\u2019s works, a wheelchair-ridden Edgar Ray Killen appears to brag about the murders he committed as a member of the Klan; that opera alternates between the civil rights movement and the end of the Civil War and is called<em> Appomattox</em>. One of this man\u2019s operas features the funeral of Amenhotep III and the \u201cHymn of the Sun,\u201d and another includes a series of \u201cknee plays.\u201dFor ten points, name this American composer whose<em> Akhenaten</em> is part of a trilogy with<em> Einstein on the</em> <em>Beach</em>.", "answer": "Philip<b> Glass</b> BONUS:<em> Akhenaten</em> and<em> Einstein on the Beach</em> are parts of Glass\u2019s<em> Portrait</em> trilogy, as is this work about three nonviolent activists: Leo Tolstoy, Martin Luther King, and Mahatma Gandhi. ANSWER:<b> Satyagraha</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1988, electoral fraud in this country was explained by the phrase \u201cthe system crashed,\u201d which was later declared to be a lie by outgoing President Miguel de la Madrid. This country, whose ruling party was described as \u201cthe perfect dictatorship,\u201d put down a revolt at the Plaza de Tres Culturas in the Tlatelolco neighborhood during the 1968 Summer Olympics. From 1929 to 2000, the PRI controlled the Presidency of, for ten points, what country that recently elected Andr\u00b4es Manuel L\u00b4opez Obrador?", "answer": "<b> M\u00b4exico</b> (or the<b> United Mexican States</b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s attempts to take the Saintonge were completely defeated at the Battle of Taillebourg. This man later forgave rebels who had captured him at the Battle of Lewes in</b> <b>his Dictum of Kenilworth, which only stipulated fines. After a (+)</b> <b>papal bull exempted</b> <b>this man from the Provisions of Oxford, he was forced to fight the Second (*)</b> Baron\u2019s War, eventually winning at the Battle of Evesham. For ten points, name this Plantagenet king who feuded with Louis IX and Simon de Montfort, was succeeded by Edward I, and ruled England in the 13th century.", "answer": "<b> Henry III</b> (or<b> Henry of Winchester</b>; prompt on Henry)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>After this event, the residents of New York gave a small gold box as a token of gratitude to one of its participants. James DeLancey\u2019s appointment as colonial Chief Justice after</b> <b>the firing of Lewis Morris was a central cause of this event, which began with a (+)</b> <b>sharp</b> <b>criticism of William Cosby. Andrew Hamilton represented this event\u2019s central figure, who (*) </b> published the<em> New York Weekly Journal</em>. Truth was upheld as a defense against libel in, for ten points, what 1735 case against a German-American journalist, an early American victory for freedom of the press?", "answer": "libel trial of John Peter<b> Zenger</b> (accept descriptions thereof)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Schools called</b><em><b> Nizamiyyah</b></em><b> were established in this empire, whose rulers sought guidance from a vizier\u2019s manual, the \u201cBook of Government.\u201d This empire\u2019s founder, Tughril, won the</b> <b>Battle of Dandanaqan over the (+)</b> <b>Ghaznavids. An entity administered by this empire</b> <b>was rivaled by the Danishmends and lost to the Mongols at the Battle of Kose Dag. That offshoot of this empire, the (*) </b> Sultanate of Rum, was created after Byzantine Emperor Romanos IV was captured at the Battle of Manzikert. Malik Shah I and Alp Arslan once ruled, for ten points, what empire that was founded in 1037 and based in Anatolia?", "answer": "<b> Seljuk</b> Empire (prompt on the Sultanate of Rum after \u201cDanishmends\u201d has been read and before it itself has been read; prompt on Turkish)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This region was the target of Operation Chastise, where the so-called \u201cDambuster\u201dbouncing torpedo bombs struck the Mohne and Edersee dams to cause massive flooding. A namesake International Authority attempting to wrest control of this region was abandoned</b> <b>after (+)</b> <b>Konrad Adenauer agreed to put its resources under the European Coal and</b> <b>Konrad Adenauer agreed to put its resources under the European Coal and</b> <b>Steel Community. Along with the (*)</b> <b>Steel Community. Along with the (*)</b> Saarland, French troops were deployed in this region until reparations could be repaid at the end of World War I. Gelsenkirchen and Dortmund are cities of, for ten points, what steel producing valley of Germany?", "answer": "<b> Ruhr</b> Valley (prompt on Germany; do not accept or prompt on Rhineland)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points name this dynasty that ruled the Kievan Rus, and later Russia, until the Time of Troubles.", "answer": "<b> Rurik</b>id Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>After his patron refused to pay him for one work, this artist painted Frederick Leyland as an anthropomorphic bird playing a piano. This artist of</b><em><b> The Gold Scab</b></em><b> was bankrupted</b> <b>when he received just a quarter-penny in an 1877 libel suit against John (+)</b> <b>when he received just a quarter-penny in an 1877 libel suit against John (+)</b> <b>Ruskin, who</b> <b>claimed he was \u201cflinging a pot of paint in the public\u2019s face\u201d with his (*)</b> <em>Nocturne in Black</em> <em>Nocturne in Black</em> <em>and Gold: The Falling Rocket</em>. A seated woman in a black dress is the subject of an \u201cArrangement\u201d by, for ten points, what artist, who had his mother sit for the painting?", "answer": "James Abbott McNeill<b> Whistler</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Dorman Bridgman Eaton wrote this bill, whose namesake, the vice-presidential candidate on George McClellan\u2019s losing ticket in the 1864 election, served with John Sherman as</b> <b>senators from Ohio. (+)</b> <b>Roscoe Conkling and other members of the Stalwart faction</b> <b>opposed this piece of legislation, which was prompted after an event at the Baltimore & Potomac (*)</b> Railroad Station in 1881. Charles Guiteau\u2019s assassination of James Garfield prompted the passage of, for ten points, what bill that reformed the spoils system within American civil service?", "answer": "<b> Pendleton</b> Civil Service Reform Act (or Bill, or Law)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One work by this author is structured as a Socratic dialogue among his discussion group, the</b><em><b> Orti Oricellari</b></em><b>, and criticizes condottieri mercenaries. After a defeat at Prato for the citizen militia founded by this man, he followed (+) Pietro Soderini into exile and wrote a work that is often accompanied by this man\u2019s made-up biography of Castruccio Castracane. This man\u2019s most famous work holds (*)</b> Cesare Borgia as an ideal ruler, stresses the idea of virt\u00b4u, and was dedicated to Lorenzo de Medici. For ten points, name this Florentine writer who held that it is better to be feared than loved in his<em> The Prince</em>.", "answer": "Niccol\u00b4o<b> Machiavelli</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "<b>In this building, a green stone marks where a throne once sat in the Loge of the Empress. This building is speculated to hold the tomb of Enrico Dandolo, though the actual burial site was destroyed in an (+) Ottoman attack. Theodosius II established a church at the site of this building, which had to be restored following the (*)</b> Nika Riots. This building, whose pendentives allow its dome to appear to float on light, was designed by Isidore of Miletus. For ten points, name this Istanbul church commissioned by Justinian that was later transformed into a mosque.", "answer": "<b> Hagia Sophia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}